<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>New prayers and meditations with pious exhortations for fast-days pursuant to Their Majesties King William and Queen Mary's injunctions to suppress irreligion and prophaneness / by Tho. Watts, Vicar of Orpington and St. Mary Crey in Kent.</title>
            <author>Watts, Thomas, 1665-1739.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38244</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17242944</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17242944</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106275</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65322)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106275)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1162:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>New prayers and meditations with pious exhortations for fast-days pursuant to Their Majesties King William and Queen Mary's injunctions to suppress irreligion and prophaneness / by Tho. Watts, Vicar of Orpington and St. Mary Crey in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Watts, Thomas, 1665-1739.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Salusbury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fasts and feasts --  Prayer-books and devotions.</term>
               <term>Fasts and feasts --  Meditations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106275:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106275:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>New Prayers AND MEDITATIONS WITH <hi>Pious Exhortations</hi> FOR Faſt-Days, Purſuant to their MAJESTIES King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY'S</hi> Injunctions to Suppreſs Irreligion and Prophaneneſs.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Watts,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Orpington,</hi> and St. <hi>Mary Crey</hi> in <hi>KENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Except ye Repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe Periſh, <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 13.3, 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Salusbury</hi> at the <hi>Riſing Sun</hi> in <hi>Corn-Hill.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106275:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106275:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY TO HIS</hi> Ever Honoured Friend the Reverend <hi>William Aſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> D.D. Rector of <hi>Beckenham.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur late Approbation of my good and zealous deſign herein (however meanly manag'd by ſo young, help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and unqualify'd an Author) emboldens me to this Publication under your Name; which has ſo well merited of the Chriſtian Church; That I cannot but find Protection hereby, from the Inſolencies and Affronts of Scorn and Prejudice; and from all the open Injuries of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Cenſure, and uncharitableneſs: Though Pride, World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and Hypocriſie, may ſtill prove irrefragable, and conſtantly undermine the Plain-dealer: Yet alaſs! this Grievance is nothing to that common Infidelity, Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Irreligion uncontroulably revelling in this confuſed Age; and impudently confronting every thing Juſt, and ſacred; doing all poſſible deſpight to God, and his Church. This intolerable madneſs, with thoſe many-headed Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, every where rending Chriſts ſeamleſs Coat, cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud for ſpeedy ſuppreſſion; or woful vengeance upon a ſtupid People; which latter nothing ſurely can now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, but either an Univerſal Reformation, and unanimous Piety; or a due execution of Primitive Diſcipline, which the Goſpel authoriſes; which our more Zealous and Godly Forefathers exerciſed under the hotteſt Perſecutions; which the Greek Church has all along maintain'd under Turkiſh Bondage; and which alaſs! our holy Eſtabliſh'd Church could not thus long have only wiſh'd, and annually hop'd for in vain; were not here more fatal and general Corruptions, and
<pb facs="tcp:106275:3"/>more daring Impiety, than any where elſe; as conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more dreadful will be our Deſolation, which nothing certainly, but Gods infinite mercy, through the merits of our gracious Redeemer, hearkening to the Prayers and Tears of ſome faithful Sons of <hi>Abraham</hi> amongſt us, hath hitherto delayed.</p>
            <p>Now therefore ſince only gentle perſwaſion remains; ſince we are to preach in Seaſon, and of Seaſon, to Rebuke and Exhort, and not wilfully to neglect any means of informing our ſelves, or inſtructing others: And ſince we muſt be careful of miſtakes, and reſolvedly honeſt, not to concel any part of our Duty from our Flocks: And ſince it is high time for the Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord, to weep between the Porch and the Altar; and to ſay, <hi>Spare thy People, O Lord, and give not thine Heritage to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</hi> Who can blame me for, or how can I excuſe my ſelf from ſuch poor endeavours, as my double charge and circumſtances can allow, which otherwiſe perhaps might produce ſomething more correct, and elaborate, and thus far more uſeful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However give me leave, Sir, thus to attend you as my <hi>Gamaliel;</hi> and in an humble (tho faint) imitation, and even in as great a diſtance as your noble endowments, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Abilities have ſet me; thus to preſume upon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of your Zeal and vigilance, your Piety and goodneſs, your publick Spirited Charity and Juſtice, your profound Judgment and Prudence, and your conſtant meekneſs and affability, ſo well know to the World, in your many Beneficial Writings and Converſation at home and abroad. This without Compliment or flattery (which can't be here, and which has always been far from my Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per) I ſhall only mention, and thus beg your favourable accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance hereof, in Teſtimony of thoſe many condeſcending favours beſtow'd upon your unworthy,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>and ever Obliged Humble Servant,</hi> Thomas Watts.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Orpington,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 23. 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106275:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>TO HIS Beloved Friends AND PARISHIONERS.</hi> Grace, Peace, and Love be multiplyed for ever.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Friends and Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis ſmall Treatiſe I preſent you with, now, as a ſeaſonable New years gift; deſiring your candid acceptance, and ſerious peruſal hereof; and moſt humbly beſeeching our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo to influence us all with the graces of his holy Spirit; that we may ſee our Errors, amend our lives daily, and both know and do the things which belong to our Peace, before they be hid from our Eyes: For ſudden Deſolation, or impending Ruin may fall upon us; and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Death (which is appointed once for all Men) will be our infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Lot; and then we ſhall be paſt doing our ſelves any good; for in the Grace no Man remembreth God, or giveth him thanks in the Pit; and after Death follows certain judgment; and then we ſhall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, to do, but ſee our ſelves either ſav'd or damn'd to all Eternity. Wherefore as we value either, and as we believe we have immortal Souls within us, which will once be ſeparated from our Bodies, and be united to them again in the general Reſurrection, at the great aad laſt Aſſize of all Mankind: So we ſhould be careful of our behaviour in this Life; and conſtantly endeavour our utmuſt Conformity to the will of our Almighty Creator and Redeemer: Which all of us muſt needs in ſome meaſure underſtand, and which not the meaneſt Capacity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us can plead invincible ignorance of; and no other is in the leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:106275:4"/>excuſable; eſpecially, under this clear ſhining Light of the Goſpel, and the frequent due Adminiſtration of Gods Holy Word, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Communion of a viſible Church, which we have all been long miraculouſly bleſſed with, inſomuch that we (above will People in the Earth) have the greateſt inducements and obligations, both upon the ſafe Principle of our trueſt Intereſts, and upon the nobler divine Principle of Love and gratitude; to worſhip and obey our mereiful Lord; to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie his holy Name before the World, in an univerſal and ready per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of our Religious Duties; and thus to work out our own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with fear and trembling: Yet alaſs! how lukewarm, yea how cold and indifferent are the generality of us herein? Even to a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Prophaneneſs, Irreligion in ſome, and a Supine Neglect and Stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in others; and a ſuperficial careleſs obſervance hereof in moſt: How do we thus obſtinately or idly contemn and diſregard the common means of grace, and Salvation, ordain'd by our Lord himſelf, in his Church Militant here? Wherein (to be ſhort) all ſuch are moſt eminently ſinful and guilty; whom the learned Doctor <hi>Sherlock</hi> moſt piouſly and ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally confutes, and inſtructs, in his Practical Diſcourſe of Religions Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, (a Book worthy the Peruſal of every Chriſtian) out of which I ſhall crave leave to enumerate them:</p>
            <p>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l. Thoſe who wholly, or for the moſt part abſent themſelves from the Publick Aſſemblies, of Chriſtians; and theſe are of three ſorts:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Thoſe who forſake Religious Aſſemblies out of Prophaneneſs, for want of a due Senſe of any Religion, or in contempt of it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> Thoſe who forſake Religious Aſſemblies for want of a due ſenſe of the neceſſity and advantage of Publick Worſhip; who do not go to Church, becauſe they think they can Worſhip God as well at home in their Cloſets or Families.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Thoſe who plead Conſcience for their ſeparation, and ſet up diſtinct Communions of their own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thoſe who profeſs to live in Communion with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and yet are too notoriouſly guilty of ſome great miſcarriages in Publick Worſhip: Such as theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> The forſaking the Communion of their Pariſh Churches without juſt cauſe for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Irreverence in Worſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> The neglect of a due attendance on the Publick Prayers of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The neglect of the Publick Adminiſtration of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That they neglect or refuſe to ſubmit their Children and Servants to publick inſtructions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> That eithr never receive the Lord's Supper, or very rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The very naming of theſe things (ſays he) muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince all Men, who have any Senſe of Religion, how ſeaſonable
<pb facs="tcp:106275:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>this Diſcourſe is; for there was never any Age, wherein there was more need of it. And ſince Religion has ſo great an Influence upon the government of Mens Lives; the neglect or miſcarriage of Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, does not only tend to Corrupt Mens manners, but has a very ill Aſpect upon publick Affairs; which you may read in P. <hi>17, 18.</hi> And ſo for entire ſatisfaction in all theſe particulars; I refer you to the excellent Book it ſelf: Proceeding to recount ſome few more ſcand lous Offenders herein; as thoſe who diſhonour God, defame and injure their Neighbour, and defile and ruin their own Souls, Bodies and Eſtates, by the commiſſion of ſuch heinous Tranſgreſſions as theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Perjury, common ſwearing and Curſing, propharation of the Lords Day, diſobedience to Parents, either Natural, Civil, Eccleſiaſtical, or Oeconomical; Murder, Envy, Revenge, Malice or any manner of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs; Fornication, Adultery, Theft, Lying, Deceit, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Oppreſſion, Injuſtice, Luxury, Pride, Drunkenneſs, and any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now here we may obſerve, that there are no Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or ſins more poſitively and expreſly forbidden and condemn'd, than theſe, both in all natural and reveal'd Religion; in all the Morals of the Ancient Heathens; throughout the Old and New Teſtamen; and in our Eccleſiaſtical, Civil, and Common Laws; particularly, ever ſince <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> have become Nurſing Fathers and Nurſing Mothers to our Church; have interwoven her in the Security and Priviledges of the State, or Common-wealth; and thus freed her from the burning fury and violence of Perſecutions; inſomuch that thus now it becomes the more indiſpenſible duty of all that are in Authority, truly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently to miniſter Juſtice to the puniſhment of all ſuch wickedneſs and vice; and to the maintenance of God's true Religion and Vertue: which if neglected, nothing can be more ſatal to a ſinful Nation: ſince nothing can more daringly provoke Heavens vengeance upon it. And now too may we not juſtly conclude, that thoſe perſons, who will break through all theſe Sanctions, bid defiance to all the dictates of right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the ſacred injunctions both of God and Man, by continuing in thoſe notorious impieties, preſumptuouſly or deſperately in deſpight of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: are the greateſt Enemies in the World, not only to their own Souls, and private concerns, but to their Neighbourhood round them, and to the publick good of any Church and State? As on the other ſide, the trueſt and beſt Friends to all, are the Godly, Righteous, and ſober perſons; for may we not find innumerable inſtances hereof, both in reading and obſervation, how God Almighty has recall'd his angry Rod upon the Prayers and Tears of the Righteous, or Penitent; and has deſtroy'd whole Cities, People and Kingdoms, yea and once a whole World for the perſiſting obſtinate wickedneſs of them that dwelt therein, allowing the Juſt the ſalvation of their own Souls only?
<pb facs="tcp:106275:5"/>And now, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> (to refer the proſecution of theſe Remarks, and exhortations to the Concluſion, and to proceed to our Meditation) May we not all eaſily apprehend this chief cauſe of that stiff-necked and general Iniquity, which overſpreads our Land, <hi>viz.</hi> The want of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, of divine Thought, or Meditation, which renders us raſh, head-ſtrong, and precipitate, and even meer unthinking, and irrational Animals: not but that we are ſome way reaſonable and thoughtful; but in that we fix our Minds upon wrong Objects, upon meer earthly things; and place our treaſure and hearts here below; madly ſuffering our ſelves to be deluded by empty Charms, fatal Nothings, the fading and tranſitory Wealth, Honour, Pleaſure, and Vanities of this Sublunary World; and all the while neglecting the more ſolid Joys and Raptures of an Immaterial Soul; the true Exertion of her Faculties and Powers; the right uſe of that ſoaring Reaſon, and improvement of that divine Image ſtampt upon us in our Creation; which alone ennobles our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and diſtinguiſhes us from the Beaſts that periſh; and which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can render us amiable in the ſight of our Heavenly Father, and conſequently make us truly happy both here and hereafter. Oh! this therefore let us all learn and experience in divine Meditation; begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it with the great fundamental Duty of Repentance; a Duty al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways neceſſary and incumbent upon the beſt of us; ſince none can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be ſo Juſt or Holy, as to need no repentance: Hereto then I beg your diligent attention: Moſt heartily praying for the Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Aids of the Holy Ghoſt, to make the words of our Mouth, and the Meditations of our Heart always acceptable to God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to his Church.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106275:5"/>
            <head>New Prayers AND MEDITATIONS, FOR Faſt Days, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>AWake up my Soul, and conſider whence thou art? What is thy buſineſs here, and whither thou muſt go?<note place="margin">The Entrance.</note> Conſider whoſe Image thou beareſt, after whoſe likeneſs, and by whom waſt thou Created: And call to mind what Laws and Commands thine Almighty Father hath imprinted upon, and reveal'd unto thee; and then remember thy frequent and innumerable Tranſgreſſions, with the folly and danger thereof: Add to this ſome thoughts of thy great Creators infinite Wiſdom, Holineſs, Goodneſs, Juſtice, Mercy; how wonderfully hath he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd for thy Felicity? With what amazing Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath himſelf wrought thy Redemption, and how he daily calls upon thee for a reaſonable and bleſſed perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thine own Engagements? And now he thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites thee upon the moſt gracious terms, to fly into the Arms of his Eternal Love? And yet how ſloathful and backwards thou art? How blind and deformed doſt thou make thy ſelf? And how rebellious, loathſome and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful doſt thou prove? Oh think then, what will be the fatal conſequences of this ſtupidity and madneſs? See the roaring Lyon ready to devour thee; behold Death (the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106275:6"/>Wages of ſin) coming to arreſt thee; and look down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Bottomleſs Gulph of Hell, gaping for thee, and thus think how thou canſt eſcape their dreadful Jews: How thou canſt avoid their Terror, Sting and endleſs Tortures, but by ſpeedily hearkning to thy Lords merciful Voice; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately turning from thy evil Ways, preſently bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy Fall and Miſery; lamenting in duſt and aſhes, and thus exerciſing timely and unfeigned Repentance. Awake then quickly, thou drowſie polluted Soul; rouſe up thy corrupted underſtanding and depraved Will; lay thy ſelf proſtrate before the Throne of Grace; cry mightily to God for Pardon and Mercy; and begin now to waſh off thy filthineſs in the Tears of Penitence, fly to the laver of Regeneration; and pray for divine help in the due know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and performance hereof; and for this end, conſider my Soul, what is this Repentance, is it not a Sorrow for ſin? A due ſenſe and acknowledgment with an utter abhorrence of all Impiety,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> The deſcrip. and diviſion.</note> and an entire Reformation of Life: Is it not a Mourning in a more doleful manner, than was heretofore ſignifyed by the external ſigns of Sackcloth and Aſhes? And is it not a weeping, an inward roaring, diſquietneſs and grief, with ſtronger crying and Tears, then can be expreſs'd by rending the Hair and Garments, and beſmearing the Face? For this is a rending of the Heart, afflicting the Mind and Soul, creating ſuch a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Spirit, ſuch a broken and contrite Heart as God may not deſpiſe; and thus true and ſincere Repentance conſiſts of theſe three Parts; Confeſſion, Contrition, and firm Reſolution of Amendment, with actual Deeds of a new and throughly Reformed Life.</p>
            <p>O ſet about this then betimes, and view thy neceſſary Obligations and Incouragements hereto; do not the Commands of thy Creator and Redeemer at all move thee?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> The Cauſes.</note> Does not Love, Juſtice and Gratitude compell thee to this Duty? Will not the experienc'd Abomination and Odiouſneſs, the ridiculous Folly and Vanity, the ſordid, irkſome drudgery,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106275:6"/>the manifeſt Evils, Miſchiefs and dangers, and even the ſelf-puniſhment of ſin force thee to Repent? Or may not the moſt benigh and bountiful Offers of heavenly Grace and aſſiſtance, the aſſured hopes of Gods favour here, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hereafter; or the inevitable privation of theſe in inſuport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Miſery, and an Eternity of Torments, drive thee to work out thy own Salvation with fear and Trembling? Oh will neither the greateſt benefits, the moſt earneſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitations, and charming Inducements on the one hand, nor the dreaded diſpleaſures, certain Vengeance, and Terrours of the Lord on the other, perſwade thee? Or doſt thou not remember thy Baptiſmal Vows, and repeated Promiſes and Reſolutions, with thy manifold breaches thereof, adding the worſe of Perjury, Rebellion, and Treachery to the black and diſmal Catalogue of thine innumerable tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions? But further, do not Nature and Conſcience check and inform thee? Do not the inviſible Motions, and ſecret whiſperings of the Bleſſed Spirit inſtruct and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thee? And do not the ſacred Ordinances of God and his Church, whereof thou art a ſworn Member; or the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary viſible means of Grace and Salvation in the ſolemn Adminiſtration of God's holy Word, Rites and Sacraments, remind thee of all? And do not thus thy lawful Paſtors and Teachers, thoſe Stewards of the unfathomable Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Embaſſadors of Heaven, cry aloud, lift up their Voices like Trumpets, and call frequently upon thee to turn from thy Evil Ways, and live.</p>
            <p>Enough, enough, I groan under the intolerable weight of ſin, my bones are broken, my heart is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, my Spirit Heavy; my fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> The Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</note> my wounds ſtink, and are corrupt; I am abominable and loathſome; I abhor my ſelf in duſt and aſhes, in great bitterneſs and anguiſh I cry unto the Lord; I call upon my bleſſed Phyſician for eaſe, comfort and freedom; for help and Pardon; I loath the mire which I have been long wallowing in; I run with horrour and amazement from the fatal Precipice which I was tumbling down; I have laid hold upon the Horns of the Altar, and fled to the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106275:7"/>and now methinks, I am almoſt rap'd up into the third Heaven; I am riſen from death; I am flying in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hrahams</hi> Boſom; I admire and love the Life of the Saints, and I long to be triumphant with them above: Since now, my God, thou haſt mercifully cleanſed and heal'd me, thou haſt purg'd me with Hyſſop, thou haſt waſh'd me, and made me whiter than Snow, yea thou haſt made me hear of joy and gladneſs, in turning thy Face from my miſdeeds, blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out my Tranſgreſſions with thy Blood, nailing them to thy Croſs; and renewing in me a clean Heart and a right Spirit; therefore will I rejoice in thy Salvation; I will love thy gracious Precepts, and in love will I ever obey thy holy, good, and juſt Laws: O ſtabliſh me with thy free Spirit, that I may teach thy Ways unto the Wicked, and Sinners ſhall be converted unto thee: O ſatisfie me with the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of thy Houſe; let me dwell in thy Temple, and wait at thine Altar; yea thus let me live, that I may never be diſappointed of my hope: O come Lord Jeſus, come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and let <hi>thy will be done in Earth as it is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Lord,</hi> what is Man, that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be thus mindful of him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> The Subjects and Adjuncts.</note> or the Son of Man, that thou ſhouldeſt ſo regard him? Man whom thou didſt make after thine own Image; didſt indow with Innocence, ſeat in paradiſe, and gaveſt him Dominion over all the works of thy hands; yet Man who ſo ſoon fell, and was ſo wretchedly tempted to a fatal ſin by the miſerable Serpent: Man, who thus brought the Devil, ſin, Death and Hell, with all Temporal and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Curſes and Plagues upon himſelf; Yet Man, whom thou haſt prodigiouſly, thro' meer Compaſſion, and infinite loving kindneſs, redeem'd, O Father, by the Incarnation and Blood of thine own eternal and only begotten Son; and Man, of whom thou requireſt no more than Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and a godly, righteous ſober living, according to thy moſt reaſonable and upright Laws; which alone can render him happy both here and hereafter; For is not God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, O my Soul, profitable unto all things, having the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Life that now is, and of that which is to come?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106275:7"/>and yet, O Man, why doſt thou ſin, why doſt thou remain ſtill diſobedient, and prove the only Rebel of the whole Creation? Doſt thou not know that God is of purer Eyes than to behold Iniquity? Doſt thou not ſee the Devil pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing upon the weakneſs of thy Fleſh, alluring thee with Worldly Vanities, enſlaving and fettering thee, only to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thy Soul and Body for his eternal Torments? doſt thou not perceive thy barbarous Ingratitude, in making thy dear Saviour bleed afreſh, by thy blaſphemy, prophaneneſs, irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; by thy Covetouſneſs, uncharitableneſs, oppreſſion, cruelty, prodigality, worldly-mindedneſs; by thy Luciferian pride, arrogance, preſumption, hypocriſe, Schiſm, Hereſie, Ambition, Luſt, Rage, Intemperance, with all the Brutal Vices, Diabolical Villanies, and innumerable wilful Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, daily and impenitently perpetrated in the World: Why doſt thou not caſt off this old Man? Why doſt thou not ſeek to be renewed? O ſeek to the <hi>Lord,</hi> to heal thee of theſe Ulcers, and to expell theſe torturing Feavers; haſt thou not the means before thee, canſt thou not faſt and pray? (without which this kind goeth not forth) canſt thou not abſtain, and mortify, and bring thy Body in Subjection to thy Soul? canſt thou not deny thy corrupt Appetites, and reſiſt Satan, that he may fly from thee? Canſt thou not ſincerely repent, and thus, religiouſly and conſtantly, uſe all the means of Grace and Salvation? Oh canſt thou not thus take upon thee Chriſts Yoak and Burthen, which thou wilt ſoon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to be moſt eaſie, light and pleaſant.</p>
            <p>And now conſider, O my Soul, what a bleſſed Change is this to be the Servant of God, inſtead of the Devil's Bond-ſlave;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> The contrary and Compariſon.</note> a Son and an Inheritor in the Kingdom of Heaven, inſtead of being a Factor for, and Heir of Hell: Is it not better here to live innocently and with a quiet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, than to be always in a Hurricane, to be ever guilty, reſtleſs and uneaſie? Is it not better to make for thy ſelf an Intereſt with the Almighty, and become a Friend of the Lord, than to make <hi>God</hi> and Man, and thine inward Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, thy juſt Enemies and Avengers. Is it not more Eligible to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106275:8"/>be truly rational, than altogether ſenſtive; to be a Man, than a Beaſt; to be a Chriſtian than an Infidel; is it not better to adore and worſhip thy great Creator and Redeemer, to renew thy Baptiſmal Covenant frequently at the Lord's Table; and to lay hold of all opportunities for doing good, and offering to the Lord the devout Sacrifices of Prayer and Thanksgiving, which is thy bounden Duty, and reaſonable Service, than to blaſpheme and prophane God's holy Word, Miniſters and Ordinances; and to neglect all, and thus dare and provoke Heaven's Vengeance againſt thee? And thus too, is it not better and eaſier to remember thy Creator in the days of thy Youth; to repent and live well betimes; than to run the bazard of an uncertain morrow and futurity; to continue impenitent till thou art harden'd in ſin, and chained faſt in the Old Serpent's Trap; till thou art repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, and haſt no place left for Repentance? And is it not ſafer to live under Gods protection, and be ſure both of his temporal and eternal Bleſſings; to be holy as he is Holy; and thus to anticipare Heaven's Joys, and reſemble upon Earth the inconceivable felicities and glories above; than to be diſcarded an abandoned to the roaring Lyon, and all the Calamities, Accidents, and Miſeries of Life; and at length to be certain of nothing, but frying in everlaſting Flames, in unquenchable Fire, and be gnawed by the Worm that never dyeth?</p>
            <p>O turn ye, turn ye then from your evil Ways,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>7.</hi> The Names and Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> ye ſinful Worms, that ye may live, and not dye: Oh be converted, and the Lord will heal you; confeſs thy ſins unto the Lord, and he will forgive the Multitude of thy Tranſgreſſions: Smite thy Breaſt, and pray to God to be merciful to thee a ſinner; eſchew Evil and do good, ſeek peace, and enſue it; weep and lament, and learn the ways of God's Commandments, and be ſtedfaſtly purpoſed to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his ſtatutes, and keep his righteous judgments: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain thy Lips from Evil, and thy Tongue from ſpeaking guile; waſh thy hands in innocency, and ſo mayeſt thou compaſs the divine Altar: Examln thy ſelf, try thy Reins
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106275:8"/>and thy Heart, and ſearch our all thy ways; acknowledg with righteous <hi>Job, I have ſinned, what ſhall I do unto thee, O thou preſerver of Men,</hi> Job 9.20. Relent, cry, and be ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful with Holy <hi>David,</hi> and the Lord will pardon thy ſin; run to Chriſt with <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and lye at his feet weeping, till his grace and compaſſion raiſe thee up: Call to mind all thine impiety, and then retire with St <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>weep bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Luk. 22.62. Know, that the Lord is gracious, long-ſuffering and of great goodneſs, and that he willeth not the death of the Wicked, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.11. but that the Wicked turn from his way and live: <hi>O turn ye from your evil ways, for why will ye dye, O houſe of Iſrael?</hi> Now this does God admoniſh his Miniſters (under the Title and duty of Watch-Men) to forewarn his people of, denouncing death to either of them that neglect their Duty, as may be ſeen in the beginning of this Chapter: Draw near then, thou ſtubborn or ignorant ſinner, come for thy Souls good to thy Spiritual guide, as thou wouldſt for thy Body and Eſtate to the Phyſician, and the Lawyer? Yea, is not thy Soul more precious, and oughteſt thou not to be more zealous for, and carefull of it? And ſo in all its ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to ſend for the Elders of the Church, thy lawful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to pray over thee, as St. <hi>James</hi> directs, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 14. And know what God declares by his Prophet <hi>Malachy,</hi> c. 2. v. 9. <hi>That the Prieſts Lips ſhould keep knowledge, and they ſhould hear the Law at his Mouth, for he is the Meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> O therefore attend upon our ſacred Miniſtry, keep holy the Lords day, and joyn with us at all times poſſible, in all our publick Duties, eſpecially in that moſt neceſſary one at the Lords Table, in devout obedience to our dying Saviour's own holy Inſtitution and Command, to eat his Fleſh, and drink his Blood; that we may have eternal Life, and he may raiſe us up at the laſt day; and that we may dwell in him, and he in us, according to his gracious Promiſe in <hi>John</hi> 6.54, 55, 56. And thus too as Chriſt has moſt exceedingly loved us, ſo ought we to love one another, which is his poſitive Commandment, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.12. and upon this has he left his bleſſed Legacy of Peace amongſt us: Now how can the Tranſgreſſors of theſe Commands
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106275:9"/>pretend to be Chriſtians? Who can know them to be Chriſt's Diſciples? and how can they hope to be ſaved con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Goſpel Covenant? Oh therefore conſider this, thou irreligious Soul, and know thy ſelf to be in a ſtate of damnation, as long as thou continueſt in this ſtate of ſin: Oh conſider and repent quickly; and ſo for this end, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> adviſes, c. 13. v. 16, 17. <hi>To do good, and to Communicate forget not, for with ſuch ſervices God is well pleaſed.</hi> Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves, for they watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give account, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you. Pray for us, for we truſt we have a good Conſcience, in all things wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to live honeſtly. And as St. <hi>Paul</hi> admoniſhes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. Let a Man <hi>ſo account of us as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſteries of God.</hi> Moreover 'tis requir'd in Stewards that a Man be found faithful: And accordingly will God protect us in our Duty, vindicate our Wrongs; and (for inſtance,) even accounts the defrauding of our very temporal maintenance, a robbing of himſelf; for does not God thus expoſtulate with the ſacrilegious herein, by his Prophet <hi>Malachy,</hi> chap. 3. v. 8, 9. <hi>Will a Man rob God? yet ye have robbed me: And ye ſay, Wherein have we robbed thee? in Tythes and Offerings; You are curſed with a Curſe; for ye have robbed me, even this whole Nation.</hi> And now that this is appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to us under the Goſpel; and that we have the ſame divine Right and Support herein, is clearly evident in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13, 14. <hi>Do ye not know, that they who miniſter about holy things, live of the Sacrifice; and they who wait at the Altar, are partakers with the Altar?</hi> Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they who preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel: And the reaſon hereof is plain, in verſe 12. If we have ſown unto you ſpiritual things, is it a great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if we ſhall reap your worldly things? And further, to add a few more Scripture Teſtimonies for a general Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: Ought not every Parent and head of a Family, to reſolve with <hi>Joſhua</hi> c. 24.15. <hi>As for me and my houſe we will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106275:9"/>ſerve the Lord.</hi> And with holy <hi>David, That only they who fear the Lord, ſhall dwell in his Houſe, that a Lyar ſhall not dwell in his ſight, that the ungodly ſhall be far from him, and that he will not know a wicked Perſon.</hi> And with <hi>Solomon, To train up their Children in the way they ſhould go, that when they are old, they may not depart from it,</hi> Prov. 22.6. And for effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this, uſe good Converſation, Reading, and Praying with thy Family; and conſtantly reſort to God's Houſe of Prayer, with all Reverence, Devotion, Humility, and Piety, behaving thy ſelf in all decently, orderly, according to the moſt excellent Rules of our eſtabliſh'd Church, wherein hold ye faſt the Profeſſion of your Faith without wavering, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the aſſembling of your ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is: For thus God hath ſhewed thee Man, what is good; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, to love mercy, and walk humbly with thy God, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8. Thus I draw to a concluſion; proceeding to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Rules of our Meditation: As,</p>
            <p>O taſte then, my Soul, and ſee, how good the Lord my ſtrength is!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>8.</hi> The Taſte of our Meditation.</note> Chuſe now to go to the Houſe of Mourning, rather than the Houſe of Feaſting. Is not one day in the Lords Courts better than a thouſand? And who would not rather be a Door-keeper in the Houſe of his God, than to dwell in Tents of Ungodlineſs? Yea, wouldſt thou not chuſe rather Affliction with the People of God, than to enjoy the Pleaſures of Sin for a Seaſon? But O how amiable are thy Dwellings, thou Lord of Hoſts! My Soul hath a deſire and longing to enter into the Courts of the Lord; my Heart and my Fleſh rejoyce in the living God. Bleſſed are they that dwell in thy houſe; they will be always praiſing thee. Bleſſed is the Man whoſe ſtrength is in thee, in whoſe Heart are thy ways, who going through the vale of Miſery, uſe it for a Well, and the Pools are filled with Water; they will go from ſtrength to ſtrength, and unto the God of Gods appeareth every one of them in <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106275:10"/>
            <p>But O my vileneſs and corruption!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>9.</hi> The Complaint, the Wiſh, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note> behold I was born in ſin, and in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did my Mother conceive me: My Nature is wholly tainted and defil'd; I am all over wounds, and bruiſes, and putrifying Sores: I have too long liv'd in Ungodlineſs; I have Eyes to pluck out, and hands to cut off; I have too many bewitching Darlings to part with; and I am overwhelm'd with evil, peſter'd with infections, cover'd with guiltineſs, and ſurrounded with char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and violent Temptations. O would to God I had never known theſe! Would I had begun the real renouncing of them ſooner! Would I had endeavour'd after a more early Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and more timely performance of my Vows and Duty! But yet, O Lord, thou wilt not caſt me off uttely; thou only canſt raiſe me, and make me clean: Tho' my horrible guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs makes me tremble to approach thee; yet where ſhall my polluted Soul be waſht, if not in the Fountain which thou haſt open'd for ſin, and for uncleanneſs; tho the Fleſh is weak, yet the Spirit is ready, and willing; and tho' after all, my beſt Righteouſneſſes will be but as filthy Rags; and when I have done my utmoſt, I muſt ſtill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelf an unprofitable Servant: Yet ſay the word only, O my God, I will, be thou clean.</p>
            <p>O Lord God of Hoſts, hear my Prayer; hearken O God of <hi>Jacob;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> The Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me O Lord after thy great Goodneſs, and according to the multitude of thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, do away mine Offences: Accept of my infirm Faith and Repentance, and grant me the application of my Saviour's Merits and unſinning Obedience; then and thus alone can I be preſented pure and unblameable, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reproveable in thy ſight. This, O Lord, I believe upon my ſincere Repentance; this thou haſt promis'd; and thus haſt thou receiv'd returning Sinners; yea, thus haſt thou met the Prodigal Sons.</p>
            <p>Why doſt thou doubt then, O my Soul?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>11.</hi> Laſtly, the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, Confidence, and Thankſgiving.</note> Why art thou ſo full of heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo diſquieted within me? Put thy truſt in God, for he is thy Helper,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106275:10"/>and the ſtrength of thy Salvation; thou art ſecure and happy in the Divine Word; thy Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Humility, Contrition, thy Love and Devotion are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; the guilt of thy ſin is waſh'd away in thy Saviour's Blood; and the power thereof ſubdu'd by his grace: Thy loathſom Iſſues are already ſtanched, and thy Sickneſſes will not be unto death, but to the glory of God's Mercy in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning, to the glory of his grace in purifying ſo polluted a Wretch. Chriſt is thy ranſom, the Holy Spirit thy guide, and the Almighty Father thy qeconciled Friend and Protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or. Fear not then, my Soul, only ſin no more; beware both of Preſumption and Deſpair; and in an holy awe and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence endeavour to ſight manfully under Chriſt's Banner, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sin, the World, and the Devil, and to continue his faithful Souldier and Servant unto thy lives end. For the Lord God is thy Light, and Defence; the Lord will give Grace and Worſhip, and no good thing will he with-hold from them that live a godly Life. O ſing Praiſes, ſing Praiſes unto our God, ſing Praiſes to our King and Saviour! O ſing ye Praiſes with underſtanding! While I live will I praiſe the Lord; yea, as long as I have any breath, I will ſing Praiſes unto my God. <hi>Glory be to the Father and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghoſt, as it was in the beginning is now, and ever ſhall be world without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now thus have I briefly gone thro' the Rules laid down by the Godly and Learned Biſhop</hi> Hall <hi>in his</hi> Art of Divine Meditation; <hi>whereto, as alſo to the pious</hi> Dr. Horneck<hi>'s</hi> Great Law of Conſideration, <hi>I refer the Readers, for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Inſtruction in this uſeful, excellent, and neceſſary Duty; which ranſacks our deep, and falſe hearts, weans us from the World, finds out and expels our ſecret Enemies, which prevents tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, chears up our Solitarineſs, tempers our occaſions of Delight, gives more light to our Knowledge, more heat to our Affections, and more life to our Devotion, Repentance, and holy Living, wherewith we ought to begin, proceed, and end every Year, and Day, to our laſt hour. Thus may we grow to be (as we ought) Strangers and Pilgrims upon Earth; and out of a right eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106275:11"/>of all earthly Things, into a ſweet fruition of inviſible Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts. In a word, thus we ſee our Saviour with</hi> Stephen; <hi>talk with God, as</hi> Moſes; <hi>and are raviſh'd with St.</hi> Paul <hi>into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; and ſo qualify'd for the eternal</hi> Hallelujahs <hi>above.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A Morning Prayer for Family or Cloſet, extracted out of the Whole Duty of Man, and our holy Liturgy,<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and compoſed according to that moſt excellent Form, which our Lord Jeſus hath taught, and left us, <hi>Mat. 6.9.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Thou that heareſt Prayer, unto whom all Fleſh ſhould come, <hi>have thou reſpect unto the Prayers of thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and to our Supplications, O Lord our God, to hearken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cry, and to the Prayers, which thy Servants pray before thee this day,</hi> 1 King. 8.28.</p>
            <p>O Lord, who dwelleſt in the higheſt Heavens, thou art the Author of our Being; thou haſt alſo begotten us again unto a lively Hope, and carryeſt towards us the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and Bowels of a compaſſionate Father. O make us to render to thee the Love and Obedience of Children! and that we may reſemble thee our Father in Heaven, that place of true Delight and Purity; give us an holy Diſdain of all the deceitful Pleaſures, and foul Pollutions of this World, and ſo raiſe up our Minds, that we may always have our Converſation in Heaven, from whence we look for our Saviour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Strike ſuch an awe in our Hearts, that we may humbly reverence thee in thy Name, which is great, wonderful, and holy, and carry ſuch a ſacred reſpect to all things that relate to thee, and thy Worſhip, as may expreſs our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to thy great Majeſty. Let all the People praiſe thee, O God, yea let all the People praiſe thee in a firm Belief, due Senſe, and grateful Acknowledgment of all thy wonderful Works of Providence; particularly, let us praiſe thee for our common Creation, Preſervation, and all the Bleſſings of this Life; but above all, for thine ineſtimable love in the Redemption of the World by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; for the happy and viſible means of Grace, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106275:11"/>hope of Glory, ſo miraculouſly continued to us within the Pale of an holy Communion, in the due Adminiſtration of thy ſacred Word and Ordinances: And now thus more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, O Father of Mercies, let us thine unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, render thee moſt humble and hearty thanks for all thy goodneſs and loving kindneſs, as to all Men, ſo to us, and ours, day, and night, (here mentioned particular Bleſſings, both ſpiritual and temporal:) For theſe and all thy gracious Wonders of the right hand, and the left, tending to this life, and a better; let our Souls magnifie the Lord, and all that is within us praiſe his holy Name.</p>
            <p>Eſtabliſh thy Throne, and rule for ever in our Souls; and by the power of thy grace ſubdue thoſe Rebellious Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, that exalt themſelves againſt thee; they are thoſe Enemies of thine, which would not thou ſhouldſt reign o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them: O let them be brought forth, and ſlain before thee; and make us ſuch faithful Subjects of this thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Grace, that we may be capable of thy Kingdom of Glory; and Lord Jeſus come quickly.</p>
            <p>Enable us by thy grace chearfully to ſuffer thy will in all thy Afflictions, and readily to perform it in all thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; give us of that heavenly Zeal, to thy Service, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the bleſſed Angels of thy preſence are inſpired, that we may obey thee with the like fervour and alacrity, and that following them in their Obedience, we may be join'd with them to ſing eternal Praiſes in thy Kingdom to God, and to the Lamb for ever.</p>
            <p>And, O merciful God, who haſt made all Men, and hateſt nothing that thou haſt made, nor wouldeſt the death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhould be converted, and live; have mercy upon all <hi>Jews, Turks, Infidels</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and take from them all ignorance, hardneſs of heart, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of thy Word; and ſo fetch them home, bleſſed Lord, to thy Flock, that they may be ſaved among the remnant of the true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and be made one fold under one Shepherd, <hi>Jeſus Chrit</hi> our Lord. O incorporate all Mankind into thy holy Church, and regenerate all with thy Holy Spirit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving us for thine own Children by Adoption; and thus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106275:12"/>graft in our Hearts the love of thy Name, encreaſe in us true Religion, nouriſh us with all Goodneſs, and of thy great mercy keep us in the ſame, and give unto us the encreaſe of Faith, Hope, and Charity; and that we may obtain that which thou doſt promiſe, make us to love that which thou doſt command. Give us that continual ſupply of thy grace, which may ſuſtain and nouriſh our Souls unto eternal Life; and be thou pleaſed alſo to provide for our Bodies all thoſe things which thou ſeeſt fit for their ſupport, thro' this our earthly Pilgrimage; and make us chearfully to reſt on thee for them, firſt ſeeking thy Kingdom, and the Righteouſneſs thereof, and then not doubting, but all theſe things ſhall be added unto us. O God, the Protector of all that truſt in thee, without whom nothing is ſtrong, nothing holy; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and multiply upon us thy mercy, that thou being our Ruler, and Guide, we may ſo paſs through things tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that we finally loſe not the things eternal. Prevent us, O Lord, in all our doings with thy moſt gracious Favour, and further us with thy continual help, that in all our works begun, continu'd and ended in thee, we may glorify thy holy Name, and finally by thy mercy obtain everlaſting Life. Grant O Lord, that the courſe of this World may be ſo peaceably ordered by thy governance, that thy Church may joyfully ſerve thee in all godly quietneſs. And grant, that all thoſe who do lean only upon the hope of thy heavenly grace, may evermore be defended by thy mighty power.</p>
            <p>Heal our Souls, O Lord, for we have ſinned againſt thee; let thy tender Mercies abound towards us in the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all our Offences: <hi>[Here mention particular Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions:]</hi> And grant, O Lord, that we may never forfeit this pardon of thine, by denying our's to our Brethren; but give us thoſe Bowels of Compaſſion to others, which we ſtand in ſo much greater need of from thee; that we may forgive as fully and finally upon Chriſt's Command and Example, as we deſire to be forgiven for his Merits and Interceſſion.</p>
            <p>O Lord, we have no ſtrength againſt thoſe multitudes of Temptations that daily aſſault us, only our eyes are upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106275:12"/>thee; O be thou pleaſed either to reſtrain them, or aſſiſt us, and in thy faithfulneſs ſuffer us not to be tempted above that we are able; but in all our Temptations make us a way to eſcape, that we be not overcome by them, but may, when thou ſhalt call us to it, reſiſt even unto Blood, ſtriving againſt ſin; that we being faithful unto death, thou mayeſt give us the Crown of Life. O remember not, Lord, our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor the iniquities of our Fore-fathers, neither take thou vengeance of our Sins; but ſpare us, good Lord, ſpare thy People, whom thou haſt redeemed with thy moſt precious Blood. Spare us good Lord, and deliver us from all Evil and Miſchief, from Sin, from the crafts and aſſaults of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, from thy Wrath, and from everlaſting Damnation; from all blindneſs of Heart, from Pride, Vain-Glory, and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie; from Envy, Hatred, and Malice, and all Uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs; from Fornication, and all other deadly Sin, and from the deceits of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; from Lightning and Tempeſt, from Plague, Peſtilence, and Famine, from Battel and Murder, and from ſudden Death; from all Sedition, Privy Conſpiracy, and Rebellion, from all falſe Doctrine, Hereſie, and Schiſm, from hardneſs of Heart, and contempt of thy Word and Commandment, good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>O Lord, our heavenly Father, Almighty and Everlaſting God, who haſt ſafely brought us to the beginning of this day, defend us, we pray thee, in the ſame with thy mighty Power; and grant that this day we fall into no ſin, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther run into any kind of danger; but that all our doings may be order'd by thy governance, to do always that which is righteous in thy ſight. And vouchſafe, O Lord, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, to direct, ſanctifie, and govern both our Hearts and Bodies in the ways of thy Laws, and in the Works of thy Commandments; that through thy moſt mighty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, both here, and ever, we may be preſerved in Body and Soul, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Almighty and everlaſting God, who by thy holy Apoſtles haſt taught us to make Prayers, and Supplications, and to give thanks for all Men; we humbly beſſeech thee moſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106275:13"/>mercifully to receive theſe our Prayers, which we offer to thy Divine Majeſty; beſeeching thee to inſpire continually the Univerſal Church with the Spirit of Truth, Unity, and Concord: And grant, that all they that do confeſs thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Name, may agree in the truth of thy holy Word, and live in Unity and godly Love. We beſeech thee alſo to ſave and defend all Chriſtian Kings, Princes, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; and eſpecially thy Servants <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> our King and Queen, that under them we may be godly and quietly govern'd: And grant unto their whole Council, and to all that are put in Authority under them, that they may truly and indifferently miniſter Juſtice, to the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Wickedneſs and Vice, and to the maintainance of God's true Religion and Vertue. Give grace, O heavenly Father, to all Biſhops, and Curates, (more particularly to thoſe under whoſe care thou haſt placed us) that they may both by their Life and Doctrine ſet forth thy true and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Word, and rightly and duly adminiſter thy holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: And to all thy People give thy heavenly grace, (and eſpecially to us, and ours, all ſorts of Relations, Friends, Benefactors, and even to our Enemies) that with meek hearts, and due reverence we may ever hear and receive thy holy Word, and Ordinances, truly ſerving thee in holineſs and righteouſneſs all the days of our Life. And we moſt humbly beſeech thee of thy goodneſs, O Lord, to comfort and ſuccour all them, who in this tranſitory Life are in trouble, ſorrow, need, ſickneſs, or any other Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (eſpecially our afflicted Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) And we alſo bleſs thy holy Name for all thy Servants departed this Life in thy faith and fear; beſeeching thee to give us grace ſo to follow their good Examples, that with them we may be partakers of thy heavenly Kingdom. Grant this, O Father, for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt's</hi> ſake, our only Mediator and Advocate. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hear us, and graciouſly anſwer our Petitions; for thou art the good King over all the Earth, whoſe Power is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and art able to do for us above all that we can ask or think; and to whom belongeth the Glory of that good thou workeſt in us or for us. Therefore Bleſſing, Honour,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106275:13"/>Glory, and Power, be unto him that ſitteth upon the Throne, to our God for ever an ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this, O God, and whatſoever thou knoweſt beſt for us, in reſpect both to this life, and that which is to come, we do earneſtly and penitently beg through the ſatisfactory Merits and Interceſſion, and in the ſacred Name and Words of our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Redeemer, as himſelf hath taught, and commanded us when we pray, to ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the love of God, and the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Holy Ghost be with us all evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <head>Holy Vows and Meditations.</head>
            <p>GOOD Prayers never came weeping home. I am ſure, I ſhall receive either what I ask, or what I ſhould ask.</p>
            <p>It is the baſeſt Love of all others that is for a Benefit; for herein we love not another, ſo much as our ſelves: Tho' there were no Heaven, O Lord, I would love thee; now there is one, I will eſteem it, I will deſire it: Yet ſtill I will love thee for thy goodneſs-ſake; thy ſelf is reward ſufficient. As it is a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py neceſſity that enforceth to good; ſo is that next happy which hinders from Evil.</p>
            <p>Not only commiſſion makes a Sin; a Man is guilty of all the Sins he hateth not: If I cannot avoid all, I will yet hate all Sin, and abſtain from all Appearance of Evil. I will loath every Evil for it's own ſake: I will do good, but not truſt to it: If it be well-accepted, it is well; if not my thanks is with God. I will not be more afraid of doing good things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, than of being proud, when I have well performed them.</p>
            <p>The Godly ſow in Tears, and reap in Joy; the Seed-time is commonly wateriſh, and lowring; I will be content with a wet Spring, ſo <hi>I</hi> may be ſure of a clear and joyful Harveſt.</p>
            <p>Nothing ſhall more joy me, than my inward Quietneſs.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106275:14"/>
            <p>Whatever become of my Body, Reputation or Eſtate here, I will ever labour to find ſomewhat added to the Stature of my Soul.</p>
            <p>In having, <hi>I</hi> will account that my good, which doth me good. <hi>I</hi> account it the only valour to remit a wrong; and will applaud it to my ſelf, as Right, Noble, and Chriſtian, that <hi>I</hi> might hurt, and will not. If it be ill with me on Earth, it is well my Torment is ſo ſhort, and ſo eaſie: I will not be ſo covetous to hope for two Heavens. Henceforth <hi>I</hi> will envy none but a good Man; and <hi>I</hi> will pity nothing ſo much as the proſperity of the Wicked.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>An Evening Prayer for Family or Cloſet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Lord, we call upon thee, haſte thee unto us, and conſider our voice, when we cry unto thee: Let our Prayers be ſet forth in thy ſight, as the Incenſe; and let the lifting up of our hands be an Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sacrifice, <hi>Pſal. 141.1, 2.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Holy, Bleſſed, and Glorious Trinity, three Perſons and one God, look down from Heaven, the habitation of thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and of thy Glory, with Mercy upon us miſerable ſinners; and purifie, we beſeech thee, our carnal Hearts, enlighten our Underſtandings, and exalt our Affections to a pious Contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of thy glorious Attributes; to a Religious ſenſe and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all thy wonderful Works, and condeſcending gracious Benefits to Mankind.</p>
            <p>Thus let us learn in the profoundeſt Reverence, to adore and magnifie thy holy Name: And thus let us bleſs and praiſe thee for our Reaſon and Senſes, Health and Strength, Food, and Raiment, with all the temporal Comforts and Neceſſaries of this Life: (Particularly for the Mercies of this Day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) But moſt eſpecially for thy ſpiritual Bleſſings, and for the Fountain and Foundation of them all, thy miraculous and ineſtimable Love in the Redemption of the World by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for all the means of grace, and hope of glory. O Father of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106275:14"/>mercies, thou art kind even to the unthankful; yea, thus muſt we ever acknowledge our ſelves to have abundantly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented that gracious goodneſs of thine: For notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our daily Provocations againſt thee, thou ſtill heapeſt mercy and loving kindneſs upon us. All our Contempts and Deſpiſings of thy ſpiritual Favours, have not yet made thee withdraw them; but in the riches of thy goodneſs and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, thou ſtill continueſt to us the offers of grace and life in thy Son: And all our abuſes of thy temporal Bleſſings, thou haſt not puniſhed with an utter deprivation of them, but art ſtill pleaſed to afford us a liberal portion of them. The Sins of this day thou haſt not repay'd, as juſtly thou might'ſt, by ſweeping us away with a ſwift deſtruction; but haſt ſpared and preſerved us according to the greatneſs of thy mercy. <hi>[Here mention all particular Bleſſings.]</hi> What ſhall we render unto the Lord for all theſe benefits he hath done unto us? Lord, let this goodneſs of thine lead us to Repentance; and grant that we may not only offer thee thanks and praiſe, but may alſo order our Converſations aright, that ſo we may at laſt ſee the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of God. Grant that we may render thee not only the fruit of our lips, but the obedience of our lives; that ſo theſe Bleſſings here might be an Earneſt of thoſe richer Bleſſings thou haſt prepared for them that love thee in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>And Foraſmuch as without thee, we are not able to pleaſe thee, mercifully grant, O God, that thy Holy Spirit may in all things direct and rule our hearts; to withſtand the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; and with pure hearts and minds to follow thee the only God. And thus may it pleaſe thee to endow our Souls with theſe heavenly Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Vertues, of Faith, Hope, Love, Sincerity, Devotion, Humility, Fear, Truſt, Thankfulneſs, Contrition, Meekneſs, Chaſtity, Temperance, Contentedneſs, Diligence, Juſtice, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and perſeverance in all good. O thus be pleaſed to make us partakers of thy Kingdom of Grace here, and Glory hereafter. And thus reign in our hearts by thy Graces now, that thou mayeſt receive us into thy bliſsful Manſions above. Oh! let there be always Oyl in our Veſſels, and our Lamps
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106275:15"/>burning, ready to attend our glorious Bridegroom at the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain hour of his coming either to Death or Judgment.</p>
            <p>And, O everlaſting God, who haſt conſtituted and ordain'd the Services of Angels and Men in a wonderful order; merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully grant, that as thy holy Angels alway do thee Service in Heaven; ſo by thy appointment they may ſuccour and defend us on Earth: And that we may ever imitate their chearful and abſolute obedience to thy Commands, till we are tranſlated hence to ſing with them the everlaſting Hallelujahs.</p>
            <p>And O Almighty God, who ſeeſt, that we have no power of our ſelves to help our ſelves; in thy bountiful goodneſs provide for us daily; and keep us both outwardly in our Bodies, and inwardly in our Souls, that we may conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſupported in both; and may be defended from all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities which may happen to the Body, and from all evil thoughts which may aſſault and hurt the Soul. O continue ever to feed our Souls with the due and ſolemn adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy holy Word and Sacraments, and with all thoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py means of Grace and Salvation thou haſt bleſſed us with in the Communion of thy holy Church; which enable us to obſerve thankfully and devoutly, eſpecially in thy viſible pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip: O may all, both Prieſts and People unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly and piouſly offer up the conſtant Sacrifices of Praiſe and Prayer; duly celebrate thy Sabbaths and holy Days, and frequently approach as worthy Gueſts to thy holy Table; thus often commemorating, and beſeeching thee, O Chriſt, O Lamb of God, that takeſt away the ſins of the World, to grant us thy peace, and have mercy upon us, and never remove thy Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick from us miſerable Sinners. And be thou pleaſed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for our Bodies Food and Raiment, with whatever elſe thou ſeeſt convenient and neceſſary for our well-being here; giving us grateful and contented hearts for all, and guiding us in ſuch a right uſe of all, as may tend moſt to thy honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and our eternal welfare.</p>
            <p>And O Merciful God, who haſt made all Men, &amp; hateſt nothing that thou haſt made, and doſt forgive the ſins of all them that are Penitent; create and make in us new and contrite hearts, that we worthily lamenting our ſins, &amp; acknowledging our wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106275:15"/>may obtain of thee the God of all Mercy, perfect Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Forgiveneſs; and thus <hi>O Lord,</hi> we beſeech thee to Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve us from our Offences, that we may be deliver'd from the Bonds of thoſe Sins, which by our frailty we have committed (eſpecially this Day, <hi>&amp;c.) O Lord,</hi> we bewail all theſe our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Sins and Wickedneſſes, which we from time to time moſt grievouſly have committed, by Thought, Word and Deed, againſt thy Divine Majeſty, moſt juſtly provoking thy Wrath and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt us. <hi>O Lord,</hi> mercifully relieve us by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of thy Grace; and grant unto us, and to all thy Faithful Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Pardon and Peace; that we may be cleanſed from all our Sins, and ſerve thee with a quiet Mind. And thus too we pray thee, <hi>O God,</hi> to enable us entirely to forgive at all times, as we deſire to be forgiven; to do in all things, as we would be done by; and ſo to love one another, that all Men may know us to be <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Diſciples: <hi>O</hi> thus may our Light ſo Shine before Men, that they may ſee our Good Works, and Glorifie our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven. Thus, <hi>O Lord Jeſus,</hi> come quickly, and deliver us by the Myſtery of thy Holy Incarnation, by thy Holy Nativity and Circumciſion, by thy Baptiſm, Faſting and Temptation; By thine Agony and Bloody Sweat, by thy Croſs and Paſſion, by thy Pretious Death and Burial, by thy Glorious Reſurrection and Aſcention, and by the Coming of the Holy Ghoſt: And <hi>Good Lord</hi> Deliver us, In all time of our Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in all time of our Wealth, in the Hour of Death, and in the Day of Judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O God,</hi> who knoweſt us to be ſet in the midſt of ſo many and great dangers, that we cannot always ſtand upright; grant to us ſuch ſtrength and protection, as may ſupport us in all dangers, and carry us through all Temptations. And <hi>O God,</hi> who art the Author of Peace, and Lover of Concord, give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us thy humble Servants that peace which the World cannot give; <hi>O</hi> deliver us from te fear of all our Enemies both Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal, that we paſs our time in reſt and quietneſs: and lighten our darkneſs, we be beſeech thee, <hi>O Lord,</hi> and by thy great Mercy defend us from all perils and dangers of this Night; and now and evermore be pleaſed, <hi>O Lord,</hi> to ſave us, and all Mankind in all dangers Ghoſtly and Bodily; and to keep
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106275:16"/>us from all Sin and Wickedneſs, and from our Ghoſtly Enemy, and from everlaſting Death. And particularly, we pray thee, <hi>O bleſſed Lord,</hi> whoſe Mercy is over all thy Works, to have Mercy upon all Men; and grant, that the Pretious Ranſom which was paid by thy Son for all, may be effectual to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of all. Give thy inlightning Grace to thoſe that are in Darkneſs, and thy Converting Grace to thoſe that are in Sin. Look with thy tendereſt Compaſſions upon the Univerſal <hi>Church.</hi> O be favourable and gracious unto Sion, build thou the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> unite all thoſe that profeſs thy Name to thee, by purity and holineſs; and to each other by Brotherly Love. <hi>O bleſſed Lord,</hi> how long ſhall <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> continue the vileſt part of the World, a Sink of all thoſe Abominable Pollutions, which even Barbarians deteſt! O let not our profeſſion, and our Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice be always at ſo wide a diſtance! Let not the Diſciples of the Holy and Immaculate <hi>Jeſus</hi> be of all others the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and Impure! Let not the Subjects of the Prince of Peace be, of all others, the moſt contentious and bloody! but make us <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in Deed, as well as in Name, that we may walk worthy of that Holy Vocation wherewith we are called: O may all with one Mind and one Mouth Glorifie thee the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have Mercy on this deſolate Church, and ſinful Nation; thou haſt moved the Land, and divided it, heal the Sores there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for it ſhaketh; Make us ſo truly to Repent of thoſe Sins which have provoked thy Judgments, that thou alſo may'ſt turn and repent, and leave a Bleſſing behind thee. Bleſs thoſe whom thou haſt appointed our Governours, whether in Church or State; ſo rule their hearts, and ſtrengthen their hands, that they may neither want Will, nor Power, to puniſh Wickedneſs and Vice; and to maintain God's true Religion and Vertue. Have pity, <hi>O Lord,</hi> on all that are in Affliction, be a Father to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, and plead the Cauſe of the Widow; Comfort the Feeble Minded, Support the Weak, Heal the Sick, Relieve the Needy, Defend the Oppreſſed, and Adminiſter to every one according to their ſeveral Neceſſities; Let thy Bleſſings reſt upon all that are near and dear to us, and grant them whatſoever thou ſeeſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, either to their Bodies or their Souls. <hi>(Here name all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106275:16"/>Relations,</hi> &amp;c.) Reward all thoſe that have done us good; and Pardon all thoſe that have done, or wiſh'd us Evil: and Work in them and us all that good, which may make us acceptable in thy ſight, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, <hi>O Merciful God,</hi> the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who art the Reſurrection and the Life, in whom whoſoever believeth, ſhall live, though he die; and whoſoever liveth and believeth in him, ſhall not die eternally: we meekly beſeech thee to raiſe us all from the Death of Sin, to the Life of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that whenever we depart this life, we may reſt in him; and that at the General Reſurrection in the laſt day, we may be found acceptable in thy ſight, and receive that Bleſſing which thy Well-beloved Son ſhall then pronounce to all that love and fear thee, ſaying, Come ye bleſſed Children of my Father, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Kingdom prepared for you from the beginning of the World, <hi>Amen. Therefore, with Angels, and Arch-Angels, and all the Company of Heaven, we Laud and Magnifie thy Holy Name, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more Praiſing thee, and ſaying, Holy, holy, holy, Lord God Allmighty, Heaven and Earth are full of the Majeſty of thy Glory; Glory be to thee O God moſt high.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus Finally, we beſeech thee, <hi>O Lord,</hi> to Pardon the Wandrings and Coldneſs of theſe and all our Petitions; and deal with us not according either to our Prayers or Deſerts but according to our Needs, and thine own rich Mercies in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> in whoſe bleſſed Name and Words we conclude theſe our imperfect Prayers, ſaying,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Unto thy Mercy and Protection, <hi>O God,</hi> we commit our ſelves this Night and for evermore. <hi>O Lord</hi> bleſs and keep us. <hi>Lord</hi> make thy Face to ſhine upon us, and be Gracious unto us. <hi>Lord</hi> lift up thy Countenance upon us, and give us Peace both now and evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <head>Holy Meditations and Vows.</head>
            <p>AS <hi>Chriſt</hi> was both a Lamb and a Lyon; ſo is every true Chriſtian a Lamb, for Patience in Suffering, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence of Life: A Lyon for boldneſs in his Innocency. I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106275:17"/>would ſo order my Courage and Mildneſs, that I may be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lyon-like in my Converſation; nor Sheepiſh in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of a good Cauſe.</p>
            <p>I will not ſtrive for Victory, but for Truth.</p>
            <p>I will keep my Paſſions bare, and Impotent.</p>
            <p>I ſhall rather Bow than breake to God; but for Satan, or the World, I had rather be broken in pieces with their Violence, than ſuffer my ſelf to be Bow'd unto their Obedience.</p>
            <p>A Juſt War is a Thouſand times more happy, than an Ill-condition'd Peace. In mine own Wrongs I will hold Patience laudable; but in God's Injuries, Impious.</p>
            <p>Though I find my Brother this day my Friend, and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row mine Enemy; though my Reputation's Blaſted with the Fire of Hell's Engine, the Malitious Tongue; though his Corroding Envy and Hatred encreaſe by Unjuſt Jealouſies; though he often deceives me by Hypocriſie, and Perſecutes me with Inveterate Prejudice; yet I will bear all Meekly, will forgive him until Seventy times Seven, and will ever Love my Neighbour as my Self.</p>
            <p>I had rather wrong my ſelf by Credulity; than others by Unjuſt Cenſures and Suſpitions. I will ſo remit Wrongs, as I may not encourage others to offer them; and ſo retain them as I may not induce God to retain mine to him.</p>
            <p>I will ever Believe in, Worſhip and Obey God the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt: I will Piouſly and Conſtantly attend the Publick Adminiſtration of God's Holy Word and Sacraments; I will ſerve the Lord daily according to his own moſt Sacred Ordinances; and will thus Religiouſly abide in the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his Church: I will Conſcientiouſly obſerve all our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Human Laws; and not meddle with thoſe who are given to Change. I will have but this one Care to live well; to God's Glory, and the Salvation of Souls. So let me be Free, Noble, Rich, Wiſe, Happy to God: I paſs not what I am to the World: <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106275:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
